the pl plus of the ecosystem probably
even more runs on some Fork of webkit
and the rest runs on Firefox which is
kind of valant trying to hold its own as
an alternative and uh is uh doing pretty
well it's one of the browsers that I use
but like you can see right like there
there there are natural pressures toward
um you know homogenization and toward
one implementation winning and ethereum
actually has managed to Buck this trend
so in ethereum um two years ago this
chart was worse and so ethereum's uh
decentralization is not only able to not
get worse but it's also able to actively
respond to problems that exist and over
time push to make them better if you
building an application that you needed
to exist 5 years from now 10 years from
now and that you want to be robust and
continue working five or 10 years from
now the what properties do you want the
chain you're building on to have I think
properties like these are exactly what
you would be looking
for with 32 eth or with less than 32 eth
if you join a pool there's more and more
really interesting pool options that are
appearing um there's even you know
things like oall Squad staking like the
there's options around
okay um there's options around like
basically creating smaller pools with
your friends there's different pools
that follow all kinds of different rules
and so there's lots of different ways
for you to become a Staker and if you're
a Staker then you become part of this
network of nodes that is securing the
ethereum blockchain so earn rewards
while securing ethereum so know I guess
uh this is know how the foundation
propaganda describes that it has a cute
elephant uh so good cheers for the
elephant uh so you know you two can join
the network and you two can help secure
it so also even if you're not a Staker
you can also run an ethereum node and
you could verify the chain
so this is uh a computer I mean I guess
these days nobody even has desktops that
look like this right it's like you
either have laptops or you have like
some crazy like GPU construction that's
like basically like looks almost like a
server right but like I don't know I
mean I just like shoved like a desktop
computer into stable diffusion 3.5 and
it like put this out so that's the
computer you get uh but uh you know you
can run an ethereum node on your
computer and you can verify the ethereum
chain right so this is really important
because if you have users that are
verifying the chain then even a majority
of the stakers acting together even two3
of the stakers acting together are not
able to change the rules on people
without everything breaking right
there's the ethereum rules they can only
change
through a hardk that is agreed upon
through wide Community consensus they
cannot be pushed through by a majority
or super majority of the stakers and
this is something that is really key and
really important and makes blockchains
very different from almost any other
kind of protocol and I think this is one
of those things that's really valuable
and really important to preserve I
think even among blockchain ecosystems
it's basically Bitcoin and eum that
really have a strong um culture of like
really at least among the large ones
right of of of actually trying to make
it possible and keep improving people's
ability to verify the chain and there's
a lot of protocol upgrades that are
coming that precisely have the goal of
making it even easier to verify the
chain so today um you have this uh
tomorrow uh you will uh be able be able
to one run node without requiring more
than a small amount of storage using
stateless clients so this is uh in my
big like series of six posts this is
going to be the one on the verge right
so stateless clients is a very important
section light clients uh so there's a
project called Helios which is doing a
form of light verification of the chain
so light verification is not perfect it
still follows the consensus and so if
51% of nodes change the rules you are
going to follow them but but it does
mean that if you're using a light client
that you do not have to trust an RPC
node to tell you any kind of information
about the chain and so Helios is uh
building a light client for ethereum
that does verification of the proof of
stake part of uh ethereum and uh also
actually starting to build light clients
for l2s um as well the longer term
future of course is we want to snark the
whole chain and once we snark the whole
chain you will be able to verify the
ethereum rules on extremely large or
extremely tiny Hardware so node writing
requirements and pushing those down is a
key part of the ethereum road map going
forward also uh staking with with less
eth this is one of those very active
research requirements right so 32 eth
it's still high and uh you know it's
even higher than it was two weeks ago
but my my okay
[Applause]
but you know my think like I would like
for people to be stakers with one e and
so I think there's a different ways to
do this there is orbit there is uh just
making a large number of aggregation
improvements but there's a lot of
protocol improvements that are coming
specifically in order to make staking
easier and more accessible and to make
running a node that verifies the chain
easier and more accessible so what runs
on the ethereum L1 so some high value
application use cases so a lot of high
value defi runs on L1 um ens is uh
currently on L1 though it's uh
increasingly doing doing more and more
with uh layer twos then uh a lot of
uh diff various applications um all kind
just all kinds of things in every
category uh people just hold assets on
layer one so lots of high value